<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<eml:eml packageId="knb-lter-knz.4.18"
  system="https://pasta.edirepository.org"
  xmlns:eml="https://eml.ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.2.0"
  xmlns:stmml="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:schemaLocation="https://eml.ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.2.0    https://lter.kbs.msu.edu/docs/eml-2.2.0/eml.xsd">
  <access
    authSystem="https://pasta.edirepository.org/authentication"
    order="allowFirst" scope="document"
      system="https://pasta.edirepository.org">
    <allow>
      <principal>uid=KNZ,o=LTER,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
      <permission>all</permission>
    </allow>
    <allow>
      <principal>public</principal>
      <permission>read</permission>
    </allow>
  </access>
  <dataset>
    <alternateIdentifier
        system="https://doi.org">doi:10.6073/pasta/9474bf7f9e506a36ae664db049f5a4a7</alternateIdentifier><shortName>APT01</shortName>
    <title>APT01 Daily precipitation amounts measured at multiple sites across konza prairie</title>
    <creator>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Jesse</givenName>
        <surName>Nippert</surName>
      </individualName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>116 Ackert Hall, Division of Biology, Kansas State University</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Manhattan</city>
        <administrativeArea>KS</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>66506</postalCode>
        <country>US</country>
      </address>
      <phone
        phonetype="voice">785-532-0114</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>nippert@ksu.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <userId
          directory="http://orcid.org">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-7939-342X</userId>
    </creator>
    <metadataProvider>
      <organizationName>Konza LTER</organizationName>
      <onlineUrl>http://www.konza.ksu.edu/</onlineUrl>
    </metadataProvider>
    <pubDate>2023-01-16</pubDate>
    <abstract>
      <section>
        <para>
          <literalLayout>Data set contains daily records of precipitation on 10 raingauges at 10 sites on Konza Prairie. Two sites (020A and 002C; SE) have 7-day clocks (one revolution per week), 7 have 24-hour clocks (one revolution per day), and the Headquarters raingauge generates daily data and 15 minute data. The Headquarters raingauge generates data year round. The remaining rain gauges are operated from April 1 to October 31. Precipitation amounts are recorded in mm. As of 2011, the HQ 1 (7-day clock) and HQ 2 (24-hour clock) raingauges have been discontinued and replaced with an Ott Pluvio2 rainguage that began data generation March 2010.</literalLayout>
        </para>
      </section>
    </abstract>
    <keywordSet>
      <keyword>Climate/Hydrology</keyword>
      <keywordThesaurus>Core Areas</keywordThesaurus>
    </keywordSet>
    <keywordSet>
      <keyword>Abiotic</keyword>
      <keywordThesaurus>Section</keywordThesaurus>
    </keywordSet>
    <keywordSet>
      <keyword>Atmospheric Processes</keyword>
      <keyword>Daily Precipitation Amounts</keyword>
      <keyword>Hydrologic Processes</keyword>
      <keyword>Kansas</keyword>
      <keyword>LTER-KNZ</keyword>
      <keyword>Konza Prairie</keyword>
      <keyword>Konza Prairie Biological Station</keyword>
      <keyword>Rain</keyword>
      <keyword>precipitation</keyword>
      <keyword>prairie</keyword>
      <keywordThesaurus>Station Keywords</keywordThesaurus>
    </keywordSet>
    <additionalInfo>
      <para>
        <literalLayout>Headquarters raingauge 1 in operation continuously since June 1982; prairie raingauges at 004B, 020B and 002C (south end) in operation since April 1983. Raingauges at N01B, N04D (flume), N04D (prairie chicken blind) and 020A in operation since 02 April 1986. Raingauge HQ2 has been in operation since 20 August 1986. All raingauges except gauges at Headquarters are to be operated from April 1 to October 31 each year.</literalLayout>
      </para>
    </additionalInfo>
    <intellectualRights>
      <section>
        <title>Data Policies</title>
        <para>
          <literalLayout>Data Use Agreements: The Intellectual Rights within the metadata associated with each KNZ data set determines the exact data and metadata use agreement between the data user and the KNZ LTER site. KNZ LTER data and metadata may be released under the license: CC BY - Attribution (https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/). This license lets others distribute, remix, tweak, and build upon KNZ work (even commercially), as long as the KNZ program is credited for the original creation. Alternatively, some KNZ LTER data and metadata may be released into the public domain: CC0 - No Rights Reserved (https://creativecommons.org/share-your-work/public-domain/cc0/). CC0 states that data are placed in the public domain, so that others may freely build upon, enhance and reuse the works for any purposes without restriction under copyright or database law. In either case, users of KNZ data are referred to the following guidelines: "The consumer of these data ("Data User" herein) has an ethical obligation to cite it appropriately in any publication that results from its use. The Data User should realize that these data may be actively used by others for ongoing research and that coordination may be necessary to prevent duplicate publication. The Data User is urged to contact the authors of these data if any questions about methodology or results occur. Where appropriate, the Data User is encouraged to consider collaboration or coauthorship with the authors. The Data User should realize that misinterpretation of data may occur if used out of context of the original study. While substantial efforts are made to ensure the accuracy of data and associated documentation, complete accuracy of data sets cannot be guaranteed. All data are made available "as is." The Data User should be aware, however, that data are updated periodically and it is the responsibility of the Data User to check for new versions of the data. The data authors and the repository where these data were obtained shall not be liable for damages resulting from any use or misinterpretation of the data. Thank you".</literalLayout>
        </para>
      </section>
    </intellectualRights>
    <distribution>
      <online>
        <url
      function="information">http://lter.konza.ksu.edu/content/apt01-daily-precipitation-amounts-measured-multiple-sites-across-konza-prairie</url>
      </online>
    </distribution>
    <distribution
      id="10.6073/pasta/9474bf7f9e506a36ae664db049f5a4a7" scope="system"
          system="https://pasta.edirepository.org"><online><url
        function="information">https://doi.org/10.6073/pasta/9474bf7f9e506a36ae664db049f5a4a7</url></online></distribution><coverage>
      <geographicCoverage>
        <geographicDescription>4B: Ungrazed and scheduled prescribed burned every 4 years in the spring</geographicDescription>
        <boundingCoordinates>
          <westBoundingCoordinate>-96.6035</westBoundingCoordinate>
          <eastBoundingCoordinate>-96.5924</eastBoundingCoordinate>
          <northBoundingCoordinate>39.0802</northBoundingCoordinate>
          <southBoundingCoordinate>39.0712</southBoundingCoordinate>
        </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
      <geographicCoverage>
        <geographicDescription>2C: Ungrazed and scheduled prescribed burned every 2 years in the spring.</geographicDescription>
        <boundingCoordinates>
          <westBoundingCoordinate>-96.5846</westBoundingCoordinate>
          <eastBoundingCoordinate>-96.5772</eastBoundingCoordinate>
          <northBoundingCoordinate>39.0725</northBoundingCoordinate>
          <southBoundingCoordinate>39.0667</southBoundingCoordinate>
        </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
      <geographicCoverage>
        <geographicDescription>N4D : Year-long grazing by bison and scheduled prescribed burned every 4 years in the spring.</geographicDescription>
        <boundingCoordinates>
          <westBoundingCoordinate>-96.59</westBoundingCoordinate>
          <eastBoundingCoordinate>-96.5768</eastBoundingCoordinate>
          <northBoundingCoordinate>39.0896</northBoundingCoordinate>
          <southBoundingCoordinate>39.0701</southBoundingCoordinate>
        </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
      <geographicCoverage>
        <geographicDescription>N1B : Year-long grazing by bison and scheduled prescribed burned annually in the spring.</geographicDescription>
        <boundingCoordinates>
          <westBoundingCoordinate>-96.5793</westBoundingCoordinate>
          <eastBoundingCoordinate>-96.5634</eastBoundingCoordinate>
          <northBoundingCoordinate>39.088</northBoundingCoordinate>
          <southBoundingCoordinate>39.0746</southBoundingCoordinate>
        </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
      <geographicCoverage>
        <geographicDescription>K20A: Ungrazed and 20 yr interval through 2012, scheduled prescribed burned annually in the spring thereafter.</geographicDescription>
        <boundingCoordinates>
          <westBoundingCoordinate>-96.5787</westBoundingCoordinate>
          <eastBoundingCoordinate>-96.5628</eastBoundingCoordinate>
          <northBoundingCoordinate>39.1079</northBoundingCoordinate>
          <southBoundingCoordinate>39.1006</southBoundingCoordinate>
        </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
      <geographicCoverage>
        <geographicDescription>HQB : Ungrazed and scheduled prescribed burned annually in the spring</geographicDescription>
        <boundingCoordinates>
          <westBoundingCoordinate>-96.6128</westBoundingCoordinate>
          <eastBoundingCoordinate>-96.6076</eastBoundingCoordinate>
          <northBoundingCoordinate>39.1066</northBoundingCoordinate>
          <southBoundingCoordinate>39.101</southBoundingCoordinate>
        </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
      <geographicCoverage>
        <geographicDescription>HQA : Ungrazed and scheduled prescribed burned annually in the spring.</geographicDescription>
        <boundingCoordinates>
          <westBoundingCoordinate>-96.6151</westBoundingCoordinate>
          <eastBoundingCoordinate>-96.6118</eastBoundingCoordinate>
          <northBoundingCoordinate>39.1083</northBoundingCoordinate>
          <southBoundingCoordinate>39.1019</southBoundingCoordinate>
        </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
      <geographicCoverage>
        <geographicDescription>N2B : Year-long grazing by bison and scheduled prescribed burned every 2 years in the spring.</geographicDescription>
        <boundingCoordinates>
          <westBoundingCoordinate>-96.599</westBoundingCoordinate>
          <eastBoundingCoordinate>-96.5843</eastBoundingCoordinate>
          <northBoundingCoordinate>39.0913</northBoundingCoordinate>
          <southBoundingCoordinate>39.0762</southBoundingCoordinate>
        </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
      <temporalCoverage>
        <rangeOfDates>
          <beginDate>
            <calendarDate>1982-05-03</calendarDate>
          </beginDate>
          <endDate>
            <calendarDate>2022-12-30</calendarDate>
          </endDate>
        </rangeOfDates>
      </temporalCoverage>
    </coverage>
    <purpose>
      <para>
        <literalLayout>Monitor rainfall in tallgrass prairie on a long term basis.</literalLayout>
      </para>
    </purpose>
    <maintenance>
      <description>
        <para>
          <literalLayout>ongoing</literalLayout>
        </para>
      </description>
    </maintenance>
    <contact>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Konza</givenName>
        <surName>LTER</surName>
      </individualName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>Division of Biology</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Manhattan</city>
        <administrativeArea>KS</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>66506</postalCode>
        <country>US</country>
      </address>
      <phone
        phonetype="voice">785-532-6729</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>knzlter@ksu.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <onlineUrl>http://lter.konza.ksu.edu</onlineUrl>
    </contact>
    <contact>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Jeffrey</givenName>
        <surName>Taylor</surName>
      </individualName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>116 Ackert Hall, Division of Biology, Kansas State University</deliveryPoint>
        <city>Manhattan</city>
        <administrativeArea>KS</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>66506</postalCode>
        <country>US</country>
      </address>
      <phone
        phonetype="voice">785-532-7762</phone>
      <phone
        phonetype="facsimile">785-532-6615</phone>
      <electronicMailAddress>jht@ksu.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    </contact>
    
    <publisher><organizationName>Environmental Data Initiative</organizationName><electronicMailAddress>info@edirepository.org</electronicMailAddress><onlineUrl>https://edirepository.org</onlineUrl><userId
      directory="https://ror.org">0330j0z60</userId></publisher><pubPlace>Environmental Data Initiative</pubPlace>
    <methods>
      <methodStep>
        <description>
          <section>
            <para>
              <literalLayout>Location of Sampling Stations: For the APT Experiment Map, please check APT map Headquarters weather station (grid C-16): Ott Pluvio². Belfort Weighing Rain gauges: Headquarters 2 (C-16); 020A (C-30), 002C (M-31), N04D (J-27)-upland, 020B (O-28), K04B (T-23), 004B (G-26), N01B (P-23), N02B (H-22), N04D (L-23)-lowland Frequency of Sampling: Continuous sampling at headquarters weather station. Continuous from April 1 to October 31 for rain gauges on prairie. Variable Measured: Daily amounts of precipitation (mm) Methods: Precipitation is measured at headquarters by an Ott Pluvio² rain gauge (continuous remotely monitored). It was installed in March 2010 at the Konza HQ site. Data is collected and processed by a Campbell Scientific (CR800) data logger and downloaded via wireless internet every 15 minutes. Previous to this instrument two Belfort weighing rain gauges, one with a seven day clock HQ1 and one with a 24 hour clock HQ2 (equipped with a wind screen) were used to record HQ precipitation. Additionally, nine other Belfort weighing rain gauges are installed on the Konza Prairie. Gauges in R01A, 004B, N02B, N04D (upland and lowland), K04B, and N01B have 24 hour clocks for finer resolution of storm events. Gauges in 020A and 002C have seven day clocks. The prairie rain gauges are not operated during the winter months (November-March). Routine Maintenance: Charts on all Belfort weighing rain gauges require changing each week. Catch buckets in the rain gauges are emptied at the time of chart changing except when the headquarters rain gauge is winterized with antifreeze (see Belfort manual for details). Clock mechanisms require rewinding each week and pens must be refilled with ink. The prairie rain gauges are sealed with plastic in the winter. Following significant precipitation events, the level of the antifreeze/water mixture in the buckets should be checked to avoid overflow. The antifreeze/water system should be discarded and refilled if dilution of the antifreeze past levels of protection occurs. Strip charts are read and hand entered into APT011. The Ott Pluvio2 rain gauge processing program sends an e-mail to the weather station technician when the bucket is 3" below capacity and needs to be emptied. In the fall, antifreeze is added to the collection bucket, see Ott Pluvio2 manual for details. SAS formats data and generates daily date and 15 minute data from the Ott Pluvio2 rain gauge. Note: Missing data are signified with the ‘.’ Summary of All Changes: 1982: only operated one ‘HQ’ rain gauge.4/1/1983: added 20B, 2C, 4B.4/1/1983 - 4/1/1986: operating four rain gauges (HQ, 20B, 2C, 4B).4/2/1986: added K01B, N01B, N02B, N4DF, N4DU, R01A (total of 10 rain gauges.8/20/1986: added HQ2 (total of 11 rain gauges).1987: When bison where introduced to the Konza wire paneling was placed around N02B, N04D- Up, N04D-Low, and N01B.2001: 020A rain gauge now identified as R01A rain gauge – watershed name change.3/19/2010: use new rain gauge 'Ott Pluvio2'. We have the new measures from this new rain gauge. For the period of ‘2010-01-06’ – ‘2011-03-28’ added comments 'old rain gauge' in the comment column.3/29/2011: shut off the 'HQ2' and old 'HQ' rain gauge (current: total of 10 rain gauges – 020B, 002C, 004B, HQ, K01B, N01B, N02B, N4DF, N4DU, R01A).April 01, 2011: HQ1 and HQ2 are discontinued. Precipitation values now reported from Ott Pluvio² rain gauge at Konza HQ site.6/3/2018: converted apt011 data structure to long format, then merged with apt012 data; cleaned up blank cells, updated old rain gauge code to the current rain gauge code (watershed code). For additional metadata information see: http://lter.konza.ksu.edu/sites/default/files/DC.pdf For additional methods information see: http://lter.konza.ksu.edu/sites/default/files/MM.pdf</literalLayout>
            </para>
          </section>
        </description>
      </methodStep>
    </methods>
    <project>
      <title>LTER: Manipulating drivers to assess grassland resilience</title>
      <personnel>
        <individualName>
          <givenName>Jesse</givenName>
          <surName>Nippert</surName>
        </individualName>
        <role>Principal Investigator</role>
      </personnel>
      <funding>NSF: DEB-2025849</funding>
      <relatedProject>
        <title>LTER: Long-Term Research on Grassland Dynamics- Assessing Mechanisms of Sensitivity and Resilience to Global Change</title>
        <personnel>
          <individualName>
            <givenName>Jesse</givenName>
            <surName>Nippert</surName>
          </individualName>
          <role>Principal Investigator</role>
        </personnel>
        <personnel>
          <individualName>
            <givenName>John</givenName>
            <surName>Blair</surName>
          </individualName>
          <role>Principal Investigator</role>
        </personnel>
        <funding>NSF: DEB-1440484</funding>
      </relatedProject>
      <relatedProject>
        <title>Konza Prairie LTER VI: Grassland Dynamics and Long-Term Trajectories of Change</title>
        <personnel>
          <individualName>
            <givenName>John</givenName>
            <surName>Blair</surName>
          </individualName>
          <role>Principal Investigator</role>
        </personnel>
        <funding>NSF: DEB-0823341</funding>
      </relatedProject>
      <relatedProject>
        <title>Konza Prairie LTER V: Long-Term Research on Grassland Dynamics and Global Change</title>
        <personnel>
          <individualName>
            <givenName>John</givenName>
            <surName>Blair</surName>
          </individualName>
          <role>Principal Investigator</role>
        </personnel>
        <funding>NSF: DEB-0218210</funding>
      </relatedProject>
      <relatedProject>
        <title>Long-Term Ecological Research in Tallgrass Prairie: The Konza Prairie LTER Program</title>
        <personnel>
          <individualName>
            <givenName>Alan</givenName>
            <surName>Knapp</surName>
          </individualName>
          <role>Principal Investigator</role>
        </personnel>
        <funding>NSF: DEB-9632851</funding>
      </relatedProject>
      <relatedProject>
        <title>Fire, Grazing, and Climatic Interactions in Tallgrass Prairie</title>
        <personnel>
          <individualName>
            <givenName>Alan</givenName>
            <surName>Knapp</surName>
          </individualName>
          <role>Principal Investigator</role>
        </personnel>
        <funding>NSF: DEB-9011662</funding>
      </relatedProject>
      <relatedProject>
        <title>The Role of Fire and Other Disturbances in Determining Ecosystem Processes and Patterns in the Konza Prairie, Kansas</title>
        <personnel>
          <individualName>
            <givenName>Donald</givenName>
            <surName>Kaufman</surName>
          </individualName>
          <role>Principal Investigator</role>
        </personnel>
        <funding>NSF: DEB-8514327</funding>
      </relatedProject>
      <relatedProject>
        <title>Long-Term Ecological Research in Tallgrass Prairie</title>
        <personnel>
          <individualName>
            <givenName>Richard</givenName>
            <surName>Marzolf</surName>
          </individualName>
          <role>Principal Investigator</role>
        </personnel>
        <funding>NSF: DEB-8012166</funding>
      </relatedProject>
    </project>
    <dataTable
      id="434849250e532ae2029287269e677770" scope="document"
          system="https://pasta.edirepository.org">
      <entityName>APT011</entityName>
      <entityDescription>Precipitation on Konza Prairie collected at 12 rainfall gauges.</entityDescription>
      <physical>
        <objectName>APT011.csv</objectName>
        <size>1018813</size>
        <authentication
          method="MD5">f3067a2211605a3ba7b741bdd62cc998</authentication>
        <authentication
              method="SHA-1">9ef35390bbc1a2eb06f07472b68ffc9cc3f0c92a</authentication>
        <dataFormat>
          <textFormat>
            <numHeaderLines>1</numHeaderLines>
            <recordDelimiter>\r\n</recordDelimiter>
            <attributeOrientation>column</attributeOrientation>
            <simpleDelimited>
              <fieldDelimiter>,</fieldDelimiter>
              <quoteCharacter>"</quoteCharacter>
            </simpleDelimited>
          </textFormat>
        </dataFormat>
        <distribution>
          <online>
            <url
                    function="download">https://pasta.lternet.edu/package/data/eml/knb-lter-knz/4/18/434849250e532ae2029287269e677770</url>
          </online>
        </distribution>
      </physical>
      <attributeList>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>DataCode</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>DataCode</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Dataset code</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>Dataset code</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>RecType</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>RecType</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Record type</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>dimensionless</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>RecDate</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>RecDate</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>Date of sample</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>date</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <dateTime>
              <formatString>YYYY-MM-DD</formatString>
            </dateTime>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>watershed</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>watershed</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>watershed of collection</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>watershed of collection</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>ppt</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>ppt</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>precipitation at rain gauges</attributeDefinition>
          <measurementScale>
            <ratio>
              <unit>
                <standardUnit>millimeter</standardUnit>
              </unit>
              <precision>0.1</precision>
              <numericDomain>
                <numberType>real</numberType>
                <bounds>
                  <minimum
                    exclusive="false">0</minimum>
                  <maximum exclusive="false">151.3</maximum>
                </bounds>
              </numericDomain>
            </ratio>
          </measurementScale>
          <missingValueCode>
            <code>.</code>
            <codeExplanation>Missing or Not Measured</codeExplanation>
          </missingValueCode>
        </attribute>
        <attribute>
          <attributeName>Comments</attributeName>
          <attributeLabel>Comments</attributeLabel>
          <attributeDefinition>comments for the data</attributeDefinition>
          <storageType>string</storageType>
          <measurementScale>
            <nominal>
              <nonNumericDomain>
                <textDomain>
                  <definition>comments for the data</definition>
                </textDomain>
              </nonNumericDomain>
            </nominal>
          </measurementScale>
        </attribute>
      </attributeList>
      <numberOfRecords>34011</numberOfRecords>
    </dataTable>
  </dataset>
</eml:eml>
